片名:发条橘子
那就是我 阿历克斯
There was me.
和我的三个死党
That is, Alex, and my three droogs.
他们是皮特 乔治和迪姆
That is, Pete, Georgie and Dim.
我们坐在科洛奶吧
And we sat in the Korova Milk Bar, trying to make up our rassoodocks
盘算着如何渡过今晚
what to do with the evening.
科洛奶吧买新鲜的奶
The Korova Milk Bar sold milk plus.
加料奶 混合奶和人奶
Milk plus vellocet or synthemesc or drencrom
就是我们喝的这种
which is what we were drinking.
令我们回味无穷
This would sharpen you up
令我们想要来点暴力
and make you ready for a bit of the old ultra-violence.
在都柏林这美丽的城市
In Dublin's fair city
有许多美丽的姑娘
Where the girls are so pretty
我第一眼就看上了
I first set my eyes
甜心莫莉・马龙
On sweet Molly Malone
她骑车穿过我身边
As she wheeled her wheelbarrow
又穿过宽敞和狭窄的街道
Through streets broad and narrow
唱着和谐
又忧怨的曲调
Crying, "Cockles and mussels "
我永远不能容忍的是
One thing I could never stand
看见一个肮脏 丑陋的老醉汉
was to see a filthy, dirty old drunkie
在街上大喊大叫
howling away at the filthy songs of his fathers
不停地唱着无聊的歌
and going "blerp blerp" in between
好像要把他的心都掏出来
as it might be a filthy old orchestra in his stinking guts.
我从不能忍受看见这种人 不论他年纪多大
I could never stand to see anyone like that, whatever his age.
特别是象他这么老的
But more especially when he was real old, like this one was.
能给我点零钱吗?兄弟
Can you spare some cutter, me brothers?
能插进一点吗?混蛋
我不想再活了
Go on! Do me in, you bastard cowards! I don't want to live anyway.
不想在这种世界生存
Not in a stinking world like this.
这个世界有什么错?
And what's so stinking about it?
这个世界错在没有法律和秩序
It's a stinking world because there's no law and order anymore!
错在让青年们欺压老年人
It stinks because it lets the young get onto the old
像你们一样
like you done!
这个世界也容不下一个老人
It's no world for an old man any longer.
这是个怎样的世界
What kind of a world is it at all?
人类去到月球上
Men on the moon.
人类在绕着地球转
Men spinning around the earth.
在这个世界里鬼混
And there's not no attention paid
但却不受法律制约
to earthly law and order no more.
亲爱的大地
Oh, dear land
我为你而战
I fought for thee
在赌场里我们见到了比利
It was at the derelict casino that we came across Billy-boy
和他的四个死党
and his four droogs.
他们准备来玩一种古老的
They were about to perform a little of the old
进进出出的男女游戏
in-out, in-out on a weepy young devotchka they had there.
这不是那帮
Well, if it isn't fat, stinking
肮脏卑鄙的比利男孩吗
billy goat Billy-boy in poison.
你们好啊
How are thou
又在拿别人的身体开玩笑
thou globby bottle of cheap, stinking chip-oil?
来跟我们玩吧
Come and get one in the yarbles
如果你们有种的话
if you have any yarbles
你们一定满意
you eunuch jelly, thou.
上去搞他们 来吧
Let's get them, boys!
警察
The police!
快跑
Come on. Let's go!
杜兰高 95 跑起来实在爽得很
The Durango 95 purred away real horrorshow.
你肚子里会有一种温暖的振荡快感
A nice, warm vibratey feeling all through your guttiwuts.
旁边都是漆黑的树 我的弟兄们
Soon it was trees and dark, my brothers
真的乡下的漆黑
with real country dark.
我们把路上的司机都吓坏了
We fillied around with other travelers of the night
我们玩命地在路上飞
playing Hogs of the Road.
然后我们向西
Then we headed west.
下面我们要玩的是惊人的访问
What we were after now was the old surprise visit.
那绝对是一次冒险
That was a real kick
充满了笑料和超人的暴力
and good for laughs and lashing of the old ultra-violent.
到底是谁?
Who on earth could that be?
我去看一下
I'll go and see.
是谁?
Yes, who is it?
对不起 我们遇上了车祸
Excuse me, can you please help? There's been a terrible accident!
我兄弟受伤了 想借一下电话叫个救护车
My friend's bleeding to death! Can I please use your telephone for an ambulance?
但我们没有电话 请到别处找找
We don't have a telephone. You'll have to go somewhere else.
但这可是人命关天啊
But, missus, it's a matter of life and death!
亲爱的 是谁
Who is it, dear?
有个年青人 说他遇上车祸
A young man. He says there's been an accident.
想进来借电话
He wants to use the telephone.
我想你应让他进来
Well, I suppose you better let him in.
请等一下
Wait a minute, will you?
我们很少让陌生人进来
I'm sorry, but we don't usually let strangers in--
你们想干什么?
What do you want from me?
皮特 再搜搜其他地方 蒂姆
Pete, check the rest of the house. Dim
我在雨中歌唱
I'm singing in the rain
在雨中歌唱
Just singing in the rain
多爽的感觉
What a glorious feeling
我又高兴起来了
I'm happy again
我在云中大笑
I'm laughing at clouds So dark up above
上面是多么的黑
太阳在我心中
The sun's in my heart
我已准备去爱
And I'm ready for love
让乌黑的云去追逐
Let the stormy clouds chase
它下面每一个人
Everyone from the place
我从雨中来
Come on with the rain
我面带微笑
I've a smile on my face
我走在大路上
I'll walk down the lane
有一副幸福的面容
With a happy refrain
我在唱
And I'm singing
只是唱
Just singing
在雨中
in the rain
我在雨中歌唱
I'm singing in the rain
在雨中歌唱
Just singing in the rain
多爽的感觉
What a glorious feeling
我又高兴起来了
I'm happy again
我在云中大笑
I'm laughing at clouds
上面是多么的黑
So dark up above
太阳在我心中
The sun's in my heart
我已准备去爱
And I'm ready for love
让乌黑的云去追逐
Let the stormy clouds chase
它下面每一个人
Everyone from the place
我从雨中来
Come on with the rain
我面带微笑
I've a smile on my face
我走在大路上
I'll walk down the lane
有一副幸福的面容
With a happy refrain
我在唱
And I'm singing
只是唱
Just singing
在雨中
in the rain
看好了 小兄弟
Viddy well, little brother.
看清楚
Viddy well.
我们每个人都筋疲力尽
We were all feeling a bit shagged and fagged and fashed
这个晚上消耗了一些能量
it having been an evening of some small energy expenditure, oh my brothers.
所以我们又来到科洛奶吧
So we got rid of the auto and stopped at the Korova for a nightcap.
路西 你好
Hello, Lucy.
今晚忙吗?
Had a busy night?
我们也工作很忙
We've been working hard too.
原谅我吧 路西
Pardon me, Luce.
角落里有些电影制片厂的人
There was some sophistos from the TV studios around the corner
一边笑一边吵闹
laughing and govoreeting.
他们好像不在乎这个
颠倒黑白的世界
The devotchka smeched away, not caring about the wicked world one bit.
立体声唱机上的唱片放完了
Then the disk on the stereo twanged off and out.
在下一张开始前的短暂静寂
And in the short silence before the next one came on
那个女的突然放声唱了起来
she suddenly came with a burst of singing.
我的兄弟们 我感到就像
And it was like, for a moment, O my brothers
有只大鸟飞进了奶吧
some great bird had flown into the milk bar.
我感到我帽子里的头发
And I felt all the malenky little hairs on my plott
都竖起来了
standing endwise.
浑身颤抖 就像很多小蜥蜴
And the shivers crawling up like slow, malenky lizards
慢慢地爬上爬下
and then down again.
因为我知道她在唱什么
Because I knew what she sang.
那是第九交响曲中的一段
It was a bit from the glorious Ninth, by Ludwig van.
路德维希・凡・贝多芬的作品
为什么你这么做
What did you do that for?
为的是惩罚你这个
For being a bastard with no manners.
没有教养的家伙
Without a dook of an idea about how to comport yourself public-wise, O my brother.
我不喜欢你了
I don't like you should do what you done.
我再不是你的兄弟 再也不想当了
And I'm not your brother no more and wouldn't want to be.
看清楚
Watch that.
看清楚了
如果不想活下去的话 就去死吧
Do watch that, if to continue to be on live thou dost wish.
混蛋!
Yarbles!
好啊 你最好给车撞死
Great, bouncy yarblockos to you!
任何时候 我会用铁链
枷锁或镣铐来对付你的
I'll meet you with chain or nozh or britva anytime.
我并不想你毫无理由地针对我
I'm not having you aiming tolchocks at me reasonless.
根本不需要任何理由
It stands to reason, I won't have it.
你乖乖的 就不要乱说话
A nozh scrap anytime you say.
够了
Doobidoob.
也许我有些累了
A bit tired maybe.
最好不要再说了
Best not to say more.
现在到了该睡觉的时候了
Bedways is rightways now.
所以 回家去睡个好觉吧
So best we go homeways and get a bit of spatchka.
是吗?是吗?
Right, right?
是呀 是呀　　　是呀 是呀
-Right, right. -Right, right.
我是和父母一起住的
Where I lived was with my dada and mum
住在城市公寓18-A区路北
in municipal flat block 18-A, Linear North.
那是一个美妙的夜晚
It had been a wonderful evening.
现在我要做的是用路德维希・凡・贝多芬
And what I needed now to give it the perfect ending
的交响乐制造出一个完美的结局
was a bit of the old Ludwig van.
天哪 极乐世界
Oh, bliss!
极乐世界和天堂
Bliss and heaven!
那么壮丽 面带一丝血淋淋的气息
It was gorgeousness and gorgeosity made flesh.
那就像一只具有神仙气质
披着稀有绢纱的鸟
It was like a bird of rarest spun heaven metal.
或者看琼液在宇宙飞船里漂浮
Or like silvery wine flowing in a spaceship
重力已经不复存在了
gravity all nonsense now.
当我闭上眼的时候
As I slooshied
眼前浮现出了这些可爱的场景
I knew such lovely pictures.
阿历克斯!阿历克斯!
Alex. Alex!
你想干什么?
What do you want?
阿历克斯 已经过了8点了
It's past eight, Alex.
孩子 上学不要迟到了
You don't want to be late for school, son.
妈妈 我有点头痛
Bit of a pain in the gulliver, Mum.
不要管我了 我睡会就会好的
Leave us be, and I'll try and sleep it off.
那时就会没事的
And then I'll be as right as dodgers for this after.
但你已经整个星期没上学了
But you've not been to school all week, son.
妈妈 去休息会儿吧
Got to rest, Mum.
或去锻炼一下
Got to get fit.
否则 我很可能会旷更多的课
Otherwise, I'm liable to miss a lot more school.
我把你的早餐放在烤炉里 我可要上班去了
我不理你了
I'll put your breakfast in the oven. I've got to be off meself now.
好的 妈妈
祝你在工厂里一天都愉快
All right, Mum. Have a nice day at the factory.
他爸 孩子有点不舒服
He's not feeling too good again this morning, Dad.
是的 是的 我听到了
Yes. Yes, I heard.
你知道昨晚他什么时候回来吗?
You know what time he got in?
不知道 我睡得很熟
No, I don't. I'd taken me sleepers.
我想知道
I wonder
他这些晚上究竟都在哪里、干了什么
where exactly is it he goes to work of evenings.
就像他所说的
Like he says
干了一些单调乏味的事情
it's mostly odd things he does.
可能是帮别人干这干那
Helping-like here and there, as it might be.
你好 特托依先生
Hi, hi, hi, Mr. Deltoid.
看见你在这里 我非常惊讶
Funny surprise, seeing you here.
阿历克斯
终于都起床了 是吗?
Alex-boy! Awake at last, yes?
我在上班的路上碰到你妈妈了
I met your mother on the way to work, yes?
她给了我房门钥匙
She gave me the key.
她说你不太舒服
She said something about a pain somewhere.
所以没去上学 对吧?
Hence, not at school, yes?
头痛得难以忍受 先生
A rather intolerable pain in the head, brother sir.
午饭后 应该会好起来吧
It should be clear by this afterlunch.
或者晚上之前
Or certainly by this evening, yes.
夜晚不错吧 孩子?
The evening's the great time, isn't it, Alex-boy?
喝点茶吗 先生?　　没时间 没时间
-Cup of the old chai, sir? -No time, no time.
坐 坐 坐这!
Sit, sit, sit!
我怎么能有如此荣幸 先生
To what do I owe this extreme pleasure, sir?
我做错了什么 先生?
Anything wrong, sir?
错?你怎会想到做错了什么?
Wrong? Why should you think of anything being wrong?
你做了什么不应该做的事吗?
Have you been doing something you shouldn't?
只是讲话的方式而已
Just a manner of speech.
我以一个过来人的身份对你说
Yes, well, it's just a manner of speech from your
当心点 小阿历克斯
post-corrective advisor to you that you watch out, little Alex.
因为下次不是在学校里面了
Because next time it's not going to be the corrective school.
也许是在警察局
Next time it'll be the Barley place, and all my work ruined.
那我所做的一切就会白费了
如果你毫不自爱的话
If you've no respect for yourself
你也应该珍惜我的劳动
you at least might have some for me, who sweated over you.
我不是在矫枉过正
A big, black mark, I tell you, for every one we don't reclaim.
你们犯了错误的话
A confession of failure for every one of you
就很容易一错再错
who ends up in the stripy hole.
我没有干什么坏事啊
I've been doing nothing I shouldn't.
一点也没有啊 先生
The millicents have nothing on me, brother.
我说的是实话
Sir, I mean.
不要转移话题了
Cut out this clever talk about millicents.
只是警察还没有把你抓起来而已
Just because the police haven't picked you up
那并不意味着你没干坏事
doesn't mean that you've not been up to some nastiness.
咋晚发生了一些事
一些很糟的事 对吗?
There was a bit of nastiness last night. Some very extreme nastiness, yes?
比利一伙的几个朋友被救护车拉走了
A few of a certain Billy-boy's friends were ambulanced off late.
有人提到了你的名字
Your name was mentioned.
而这些话传到了我的耳朵里
The words got to me by the usual channels.
你的朋友也参与了
Certain friends of yours were named also.
没有人可以证明白己任何事
Nobody can prove anything about anybody, as usual.
我在警告你 阿历克斯
I'm warning you, little Alex
作为在这个肮脏世界里
being a good friend to you as always
你的永远的好朋友
the one man in this sore and sick community
要把你挽救出来
who wants to save you from yourself!
你吃错了什么药?
What gets into you all?
我们研究你太久了
We've been studying the problem for damn well near a century.
但我们发觉
But we get no farther with our studies.
你有良好的家庭
You got a good home here. Good, loving parents.
你的脑子并不太坏
You've got not too bad of a brain.
难道是有魔鬼爬进你的心灵?
Is it some devil that crawls inside of you?
没有人抓住我任何把柄
Nobody's got anything on me.
我很久没落在警察手里了
I been out of the millicents' rookers for a long time.
那正是我担心的 你安全得太久了
That's just what worries me. A bit too long to be safe.
你快了 凭我的感觉
You're about due, by my reckoning.
所以我要警告你 阿历克斯
That's why I'm warning you
别趟这些浑水
to keep your handsome young proboscis out of the dirt.
你明白吗?
Do I make myself clear?
我是一个没有泥污的湖
As an unmuddied lake, sir.
像夏天的天空一样清澈
As clear as an azure sky of deepest summer.
你要相信我 先生
You can rely on me, sir.
打扰了 兄弟
Excuse me, brother.
我两周前订的 你看看到了吗?
I ordered this two weeks ago. Can you see if it's arrived?
等一下
Just a minute.
对不起 小姐们
Pardon me, ladies.
你们快乐吗 宝贝?
Enjoying that, are you, my darling?
有点冷淡无聊吧 亲爱的?
A bit cold and pointless, isn't it, my lovely?
你怎么了 小妹妹?
What's happened to yours, my little sister?
你在找谁?布拉蒂
Who you getting, bratty?
歌戈利・歌戈 乔尼・治瓦格
Goggly Gogol? Johnny Zhivago?
还是天堂17?
The Heaven 17?
What you got back home to play your fuzzy warbles on?
我猜你们有小巧可爱的随身播放机
I bet you've got little pitiful, portable picnic players.
跟叔叔我来吧 听个痛快
Come with Uncle and hear all proper.
听天使的小号和魔鬼的长号
Hear angel trumpets and devil trombones.
你们被邀请了
You are invited.
你们好
Hi, hi, hi, there.
你好
Well, hello.
他来了
He are here! He have arrived!
Hooray!
好了 好了
Welly, welly, welly, welly, welly, welly, well!
我怎么有此荣幸接受这意外的造访
To what do I owe the extreme pleasure of this surprising visit?
我们有点担心
We got worried.
我们在奶吧边喝边等
There we were, waiting and drinking away at the old knifey moloko
但你一直没去
and you had not turned up.
我们猜可能哪里冒犯了你
And we thought you might have been, like offended by something or other.
所以我们到你这里来了
So around we come to your abode.
对不起
Appy polly loggies.
我头痛 要睡觉
I had something of a pain in the gulliver, so I had to sleep.
我命令醒来时自己却还没醒
I was not awakened when I gave orders for wakening.
很担心你的头痛
Sorry about the pain.
用脑太多了吧?
Using the gulliver too much-like, maybe.
下命令 定规矩 等等
Giving orders and discipline and such, perhaps.
确实不痛了吗?你上床会更好吗?
You sure the pain is gone?You sure you'd not be happier back in bed?
有话说清楚
Let's get things nice and sparkling clear.
这种讽刺 如果算得上
This sarcasm, if I may call it such
可不是你们的风格 我的弟兄们
does not become you, my little brothers.
作为你们的朋友和头领
我有权知道发生了什么
As I am your droog and leader I'm entitled to know what goes on.
那么 迪姆
Now then, Dim.
你那么呲牙咧嘴一笑预视着什么?
What does that great big horsey gape of a grin portend?
不要再欺负迪姆了 兄弟
All right, no more picking on Dim, brother.
这是新方式的一部分
That's part of the new way.
新方式
这新方式是怎么加速?
New way? What's this about a new way?
我知道有人在我睡觉时经常谈到我
There's been some very large talk behind my sleeping back, I know it.
如果你一定要 那么就去吧
If you must have it, have it, then.
我们四处游荡 打砸抢
We go around shop crasting and the like
每人弄到一点点钱
coming out with a pitiful rookerfull of money each.
而"打手"咖啡店里的英国佬威尔
And Will the English in the Muscleman coffee mesto
说他能和任何小伙子一样打
saying he can fence anything any malchick tries to crast.
闪光的东西 冰
The shiny stuff. The ice!
会有很多钱 英国佬威尔这么说的
The big, big money's available, is what Will the English says.
你有很多钱会干什么?
And what will you do with the big, big, big money?
你不是什么都有了吗?
Have you not everything you need?
如果你要汽车 你从树上取好了
If you need a motorcar, you pluck it from the trees.
如果你要漂亮女孩 你可以有
If you need pretty polly, you take it.
老弟 你有时想说的就像一个小孩
Brother, you think and talk sometimes like a little child.
今晚我们要玩一个大人玩的
Tonight we pull a man-size crast.
好极了 太棒了
Good! Real horrorshow!
动力总是给予那些等待它们的人
Initiative comes to thems that wait.
我已经教你很多了 小弟
I've taught you much, my little droogies.
现在告诉我你在想什么 乔治小子
Now tell me what you had in mind, Georgie-boy.
老样子 先来点加料奶 你说是吧?
The old moloko plus first. Would you not say?
一些让我们兴奋的东西
-Something to sharpen us up. -Some moloko plus.
你先请 由你开始
由你开始 加料奶
You got to go there first. We got a start on you. Moloko Plus!
当我们走在海军码头的岸边
As we walked along the flatblock marina
我表面上很平静 但一直在思考
I was calm on the outside, but thinking all the time.
现在成了乔治来
So now it was to be Georgie the General
命令大伙该干什么 不该干什么
saying what we should do and what not to do.
而没头脑的蒂姆 只会像狗一样傻笑
And Dim as his mindless, grinning bulldog.
突然我想起只有笨蛋才会去思考
But suddenly I viddied that thinking was for the gloopy ones
聪明人用的是 比如灵感和上帝的旨意
and that the oomny ones used, like, inspiration and what Bog sends.
现在帮助我的是美妙的音乐
For now it was lovely music that came to my aid.
有音乐从一扇开着的窗户传出
There was a window open with a stereo on
我立刻请楚了该做什么
and I viddied right at once what to do.
我没有割到蒂姆的重要线路
I had not cut into any of Dim's main cables.
所以在一张干净布的帮助下
And so with the help of a clean tashtook
血很快就不流了
the red, red kroovy soon stopped.
我也很快让剩下的两人静下来
And it did not take long to quieten the two wounded soldiers
在纽约市公爵小酒吧里
down in the snug of the Duke of New York.
现在他们知道谁是头了
Now they knew who was master and leader.
一群懦夫
Sheep, thought I.
但一个真正的领导总知道什么时候
But a real leader knows always when, like
像是什么时候向手下表示宽大
to give and show generous to his unders.
现在我们又回到了原地
Well! Now we're back to where we were.
不是吗?
Yes?
像以前一样 忘记一切
Just like before, and all forgotten?
对吗?
Right, right, right?
对
Right.
好 乔治小子
Well, Georgie-boy
你为今晚出的主意现在告诉我们吧
this idea of yours for tonight. Tell us all about it, then.
今晚不行
Not tonight.
现在不行
Not this nochy.
说吧 乔治小子
Come, come, come, Georgie-boy.
你和我们一样都是勇敢的人
You're a big, strong chelloveck, like us all.
我们不是小孩子 不是吗 乔治?
We're not little children, are we, Georgie-boy?
那么你究竟在想什么
What, then, didst thou in thy mind have?
这是一个健身的农场
It's this health farm.
稍微出城的地方
A bit out of the town.
独立的地方
Isolated.
它由一个富家女拥有她和她的猫一起住
It's owned by this rich ptitsa who lives there with her cats.
这地方已经关闭了一星期她现在一人独处
The place is shut down for a week and she's completely on her own.
那里装满了金银
It's full up with, like, gold and silver
还有珠宝
and, like, jewels.
告诉我多一点 乔治小子 再多点
Tell me more, Georgie-boy. Tell me more.
糟糕
Oh, shit!
是谁?
Who's there?
对不起 能帮个忙吗?
Excuse me, can you please help?
发生了一起严重事故
There's been a terrible accident!
我能用你的电话叫救护车吗?
Can I please use your telephone for an ambulance?
非常对不起
I'm frightfully sorry.
一里外有公用电话
There's a telephone in the public house a mile down the road.
我建议你用那个
I suggest you use that.
但小姐 这是很紧急
But missus, this is an emergency!
关乎生死
It's a matter of life and death!
我朋友倒在路上 流血很多 快要死了
Me friend's lying in the middle of the road, bleeding to death!
非常抱歉 我在天黑后 从不给陌生人开门
I'm very sorry, but I never open the door to strangers after dark.
很好 女士
Very well, madam.
你怀疑我们没有错
You can't be blamed for being suspicious
现在晚上有很多混蛋在游荡
with so many scoundrels and rogues of the night about.
我到酒吧去试试看吧
I'll try and get help at the pub, then.
很抱歉 打扰你
I'm sorry if I disturbed you.
非常感谢晚安
Thank you very much. Good night.
蒂姆 弯腰
Dim, bend down.
我从那扇窗进去再把前门打开
I'll get in that window and open the front door.
喂 莱德烈特警察局吗?
Hello, Radlett Police Station?
晚上好 我是伍德米尔健身农场的维瑟斯小姐
Good evening. It's Miss Weathers at Woodmere Health Farm.
很抱歉打扰你 但刚才发生一些怪事
I'm sorry to bother you, but something rather odd just happened.
可能没什么 但我也不敢肯定
It's probably nothing at all, but you never know.
一个年轻人敲门 要用电话
A young man rang the bell, asking to use the telephone.
他说有什么事故之类的
He said there's been some kind of accident.
他说的有一点引起了我的注意
The thing that caught my attention was what he said.
他的话像是在引用今天早上报纸里的话
His words sounded like those quoted in the papers this morning
与昨晚遭袭击的作家和他的妻子有关
in connection with the writer and his wife who were assaulted last night.
就在几分钟以前
Just a few minutes ago.
如果你认为有必要的话
If you think that's necessary.
但我肯定他现在已经走了
But I'm quite sure he's gone away now.
好的 没问题
All right, fine.
非常感谢
Thank you very much.
哈哈 在这里
Hi, hi, hi, there.
终于见面了
At last we meet.
我们得通过收信口的简短交流 可不令人满意
Our brief govorett through the letter-hole was not, shall we say, satisfactory.
你是谁?
Who are you?
你怎么进来的?
How the hell did you get in here?
你在干什么?
What the bloody hell do you think you're doing?
调皮 调皮 调皮!
Naughty, naughty, naughty!
你这个肮脏的母狗
You filthy old soomaka.
现在听着 你这个小混蛋
Now listen here, you little bastard!
转过身去 和你进来时一样走出去
Just turn round and walk out of here the same way you came in.
不要碰它
Leave that alone! Don't touch it!
那是珍贵的艺术品
It's a very important work of art.
你究竟想要什么?
What the bloody hell do you want?
女士 老实说
To be perfectly honest, madam
我正在参加一个国际学生竞赛
I'm taking part in an international students'contest
看谁卖杂志的得分最多
to see who can get the most points for selling magazines.
废话少说 小子
Cut the shit, sonny
在你有麻烦前最好滚出去
and get out of here before you get yourself into serious trouble.
你不要碰它 快滚
I told you to leave that alone! Now get out of here
不然 我会把你扔出去
before I throw you out!
混蛋 臭虫
Wretched, slummy bedbug!
我来教训你闯进别人家里会怎样
可恶!
I'll teach you to break into real people's houses.
小混蛋
Fucking
little
小
混蛋！
bastard!
我们走 警察来了 等一下 兄弟
-Let's go. The police are coming! -One minoota, droogie.
你们这些混蛋 我看不见东西
You bastards! I'm blind!
混蛋 我瞎了 我什么也看不见
I'm blind, you bastards! I can't see!
坐在那里满怀希望是没用的 小兄弟们
It's no good sitting there in hope, my little brothers.
除非我的律师在 否则我什么也不会说
I won't say a single solitary slovo unless I have my lawyer here.
我懂法律 混蛋
I know the law, you bastards.
说的很对 汤姆
Righty-right, Tom.
我们得给阿历克斯朋友展示一下 我们也懂法
We'll have to show our friend Alex here that we know the law too.
但懂法还不够
But that knowing the law isn't everything.
你的伤真丑 小子
Nasty cut you've got there, little Alex.
真耻辱 不是吗?
Shame, isn't it?
破坏了你的美
Spoils all your beauty.
谁弄的?
Who gave you that, then?
你是怎么搞的?
How'd you do that, then?
你想怎样 混蛋?
What's your point, you bastard?
是为了你的女受害人
That is for your lady victim.
你这个讨厌的、
You ghastly
可怜的混蛋
wretched scoundrel.
把他拉开
Get him off me!
你这个小混蛋
You rotten little bastard!
晚上好 戴尔托先生
Good evening, Mr. Deltoid.
晚上好 警官
Good evening, Sergeant.
他们在B室 先生
They're in room B, sir.
非常感谢
Thank you very much.
警官
Sergeant--
晚上好 戴尔托先生
Good evening, Mr. Deltoid.
晚上好 检查官
Good evening, Inspector.
要茶吗 长官? 不 谢谢 警官 待会再喝
-Would you like your tea now, sir? -No, thank you, Sergeant. We'll have it later
我能要些纸巾吗? 好的 长官
-May I have some paper towels, please? -Yes, sir.
我们正在审问犯人
We're interrogating the prisoner now.
也许你想进来　非常感谢
-Perhaps you'd care to come inside. -Thank you very much.
晚上好 士官!大家晚上好!
Good evening, Sergeant. Good evening, all.
哦 天哪这小子看上去糟透了
Oh, dear! This boy does look a mess, doesn't he?
看他这状况
Just look at the state of him.
像做恶梦一样
Love's young nightmare-like.
暴力促长暴力
Violence makes violence.
他对逮捕者进行反抗
He resisted his lawful arrestors.
这是我所不能容忍的
This is the end of the line for me.
不能容忍
The end of the line, yes.
那我怎么样 长官?
And what of me, brother sir?
为我说句真话 我并不那么坏
Speak up for me. I'm not so bad.
我是受别人教唆去做的
I was led on by the treachery of others.
很会说话 他是这样 长官
Sings the roof off lovely, he does, sir.
我的同伴在哪里? 在他们逃跑之前抓住他们
Where are my treacherous droogs? Get them before they get away!
全是他们的主意
It was all their idea, brothers.
他们逼我的 我是无辜的
They forced me to do it. I'm innocent!
现在你是个谋杀犯 小阿历克斯
You are now a murderer, little Alex.
谋杀犯
A murderer.
这不是真的 先生
Not true, sir.
那只是小事一桩
It was only a slight tolchok.
她还活着 我发誓
She were breathing, I swear it.
我刚从医院回来
I've just come from the hospital.
你的受害人死了
Your victim has died.
你在吓我 告诉我是这样 先生
You try to frighten me. Admit so, sir.
这是另一种折磨
This is some new form of torture.
说吧 先生　这是你自己的折磨
-Say it, brother sir. -It'll be your own torture.
我希望这会折磨得你发疯
I hope to God it'll torture you to madness.
如果你想教训他一下的话 请随便
If you'd care to give him a bash in the chops, don't mind us.
我们拉住他
We'll hold him down.
他一定会让你失望 先生
He must be a great disappointment to you, sir.
这是真正悲惨故事的开始 哦 兄弟们
This is the real weepy and tragic part of the story beginning
在法官和陪审讯后
O my brothers and only friends.
在对我进行了严厉抨击后
After a trial, with judges and a jury
经过审讯，法官和陪审团判决
and hard words spoken against your friend and humble narrator
他被判在84-F监狱服刑14年
he was sentenced to 14 years in Staja Number 84-F
生活在变态和冷酷的人中间
among smelly perverts and hardened prestoopniks.
我父亲惊讶地想用他那淤血手
The shock sending my dada beating his bruised and krovvy rookers
揍上帝几拳
against unfair Bog in His Heaven.
我母亲也伤心欲绝
And my mum boo-hoo-hooing in her mother's grief
为她仅有和亲爱的儿子
at her only child and son of her bosom
就像动了真格的一样让所有人失望
like, letting everybody down real horrorshow.
早上好 有一个泰晤土来的犯人 长官
Morning. One up from Thames, mister.
从泰晤士来的一个
One up from Thames, sir.
好 打开牢门
Right! Open up the cell!
是 长官
Yes, sir.
早上好 长官 这是犯人的犯罪记录
Good morning, sir. Here are the prisoner's committal forms.
谢谢 警官
Thank you, mister.
姓名 亚历山大・德拉吉
-Name? -Alexander DeLarge.
你现在在帕克库尔监狱了
You are now in H. M. Prison Parkmoor.
从这一刻起 你要称所有狱官为"长官"
From this moment, you will address all prison officers as "sir. "
姓名?
Name?
亚历山大・德拉吉 长官
Alexander DeLarge, sir.
刑期
Sentence?
14年 长官
14 years, sir.
罪名?
Crime?
谋杀罪 长官
Murder, sir.
好了 警官 解下他的手铐
Right. Take the cuffs off him, mister.
你现在是655321号
You are now 655321.
你有义务记住这个号码
It is your duty to memorize that number.
谢谢 警官 做得很好
Thank you, mister. Well done.
谢谢　让警官出去
-Thank you. -Let the officer out.
好了 清空你的口袋
All right, empty your pockets.
你看不见地上的白线吗?
Are you able to see the white line painted on the floor
就在你背后
directly behind you
655321?
是 长官
Yes, sir.
那么你的脚趾属于
Then your toes belong
线的另一边
on the other side of it!
是 长官　对了
-Yes, sir. -Right.
继续
Carry on.
拿起它
Pick that up
再把它放好
and put it down properly.
半块巧克力
One half-bar of chocolate.
一串系在白色金属环上的钥匙
One bunch of keys on white metal ring.
一包香烟
One packet of cigarettes.
两支塑料原珠笔
Two plastic ball pens.
一黑一红
One black, one red.
一支便携式梳子 黑塑料
One pocket comb, black plastic.
一个地址薄 红色仿皮
One address book, imitation red leather.
一枚十便士硬币
One ten-penny piece.
一只白色金属手表
One white metal wristlet watch
腕表 系在白色金属表带上
Timawrist, on a white metal expanding bracelet.
口袋里还有别的什么吗?
Anything else in your pockets?
没了 长官  好的
-No, sir. -Right.
在这里为你的财物签字
Sign here for your valuable property.
你带进来的香烟和巧克力
The tobacco and chocolate you brought in
现在不属于你了
you lose that
因为你现在有罪
as you are now convicted.
现在去桌子那里 脱衣服
Now over to the table and get undressed.
你今早被警察拘留的吗?
Were you in police custody this morning?
是的 长官　一件夹克 蓝色有边
-Yes, sir. -One jacket, blue pinstriped.
监狱看管
Prison custody?
是的 先生 已收到
Yes, sir, on remand.
条领带 蓝色　宗教?
-One necktie, blue. -Religion?
基督教 长官
C. of E., sir.
你是指英国教会吗?
Do you mean the Church of England?
是 长官 英国教会 长官
Yes, sir. The Church of England, sir.
棕色头发 是吗?
Brown hair, isn't it?
金色头发 长官
Fair hair, sir.
蓝色眼睛?
Blue eyes?
蓝色 长官
Blue, sir.
你有否戴眼镜或隐形?
Do you wear eyeglasses or contact lenses?
没有 长官
No, sir.
一件衬衫 蓝色有领
One shirt, blue. Collar attached.
你有没有因生大病而被治疗?
Have you been receiving medical treatment for any serious illness?
没有 长官　一双拉链黑皮靴 有磨损
-No, sir. -One pair of boots, black leather. Zippered. Worn.
你有无精神方面的疾病?没有 长官
-Have you ever had any mental illness? -No, sir.
你戴不戴假牙或假肢?　　没有 长官
-Do you wear any false teeth or any false limbs? -No, sir.
一条裤子 蓝色有边
One pair of trousers, blue pinstriped.
你是否曾经晕眩过?　没有 长官
-Have you ever had any attacks of fainting or dizziness? -No, sir.
一双袜子 黑色
One pair of socks, black.
你是否有羊角疯?　　没有 长官
-Are you an epileptic? -No, sir.
一条内裤 白色带蓝色腰边
One pair of underpants, white with blue waistband.
你现在或曾经是否为同性恋?
Are you now, or have you ever been, a homosexual?
不 长官 好
-No, sir. -Right.
樟脑球 警官　樟脑球 长官
-The mothballs, mister. -Mothballs, sir.
现在面对墙
Now then, face the wall
弯腰 摸你的脚趾
bend over and touch your toes.
患过性病吗?　没有 长官
-Any venereal disease? -No, sir.
湿疣?　没有 长官　淋病?　没有 长官
-Crabs? -No, sir. -Lice? -No, sir.
去那边洗个澡　是 长官 一个人洗澡
-Through there for the bath. -Yes, sir. -One for a bath.
下一步会怎么样?
What's it going to be, eh?
你们很喜欢二进宫或多进宫吗?
Is it going to be in and out of institutions like this
怎么不改过自新呢?
though more in than out for most of you?
你们这些罪不可赦的
Or are you going to attend to the divine word
真的要等到了另一个世界
and realize the punishments that await unrepentant sinners
面对和这一样的惩罚才会有所醒悟?
in the next world as well as this?
你们这些大傻瓜啊!
And what idiots you are
出卖人格尊严 只为了一碗残羹冷炙
selling your birthright for a saucer of cold porridge.
盗窃
The thrill of theft.
暴力
Of violence.
和随心所欲的刺激
The urge to live easy.
来吧 当我们有无庸置疑的证据
Well, I ask you what is it worth
对 铁证如山
when we have undeniable proof
知道地狱存在时
yes, incontrovertible evidence
我问问你这些又价值何在?
that hell exists?
我知道!
I know!
我知道的 朋友们
I know, my friends.
我看到过
I have been informed
在显圣时
in visions
有一个地方
that there is a place
比任何监狱都要黑暗
darker than any prison
比任何人类的火都要热
hotter than any flame of human fire
在那里 灵魂
where souls
就像你们这些犯人一样是不可饶恕的
of unrepentant criminal sinners like yourselves--
不要笑 安静! 不要笑!
Don't you laugh, damn you! Don't you laugh.
我是认真的 正如你们
I say, like yourselves
大声尖叫
scream
无助而无尽的
in endless and unendurable agony.
他们的皮肤
Their skin
腐烂了并且一块块脱落
rotting and peeling.
一个火球
A fireball
在他们的尖叫声中不断飞转
spinning in their screaming guts!
我知道 是的 我知道
I know. Yes, I know!
肃静!
Silence!
好好听神父讲
Listen to the priest!
好吧 你们这些人 唱完圣诗就结束吧
All right, you lot! We'll end by singing hymn 258
来 唱囚犯圣歌集的258号圣歌
in the prisoner's hymnal.
让大家净化一下思想 你们这些白痴
And let's have a little reverence, you bastards!
"我是一只迷途小羔羊"
I was a wandering sheep
开心唱 该死的　"我并不喜欢羊圈"
-Sing up, damn you! -I did not love the fold
大声点!
Louder!
"我不喜欢牧童的嗓音"
I did not love my shepherd's voice
"我不会受约束"
I would not be controlled
大声点!
Louder!
其实并没有得到启发!一点也没有!
It had not been edifying. Indeed not.
在这个该死的人渣动物园里待了两年
Being in this hellhole and human zoo for two years now.
被野蛮的变态打骂和欺压
Being kicked and tolchoked by brutal warders
遇到各式各样的罪犯和人渣
and meeting leering criminals and perverts
随时准备把像我、您的讲述者
ready to dribble all over
这样的好小伙子痛打一顿 就像打破这杯美酒
a luscious young malchick like your storyteller.
我自愿
It was my rabbit
参加查理神父开展的周日服务活动
to help the prison charlie with the Sunday service.
他是个大胖子 一个挺自大的人
He was a bolshy, great burly bastard.
但他很喜欢我 也许因为我很年轻
But he was very fond of myself, me being very young
而且现在也对书籍巨作产生了兴趣
and also now very interested in the Big Book.
我读了许多关于鞭刑及头戴荆棘的书
I read all about the scourging and the crowning with thorns.
我常常想像我也在其中
And I could viddy myself helping in
主管鞭打及钉手指
and even taking charge of the tolchoking and the nailing in.
穿着典型的罗马贵族服装
Being dressed in the height of Roman fashion.
我不太喜欢书的后半部分
I didn't so much like the latter part of the Book
那更类似于一种形式上的说教
which is more like all preachy talking
比不上战斗 和进进出出的把戏
than fighting and the old in-out.
我喜欢这些古老的野蛮人互相杀戮的场面
I like the parts where these old yahoodies tolchok each other
接着 用敌人的鲜血庆祝胜利
and then drink their Hebrew vino
并享受给人无尽快意的夺妻之乐
and getting onto the bed with their wives' handmaidens.
那就是我坚持下去的精神动力
That kept me going.
"千万不要做个邪恶的人
"Seek not to be like evil men.
甚至不要去想和他们在一起
Neither desire to be with them
因为他们是强盗的化身
because their minds studieth robberies
而且满口粗言秽语"
and their lips speak deceits. "
"如果你失去了希望
If thou lose hope
在忧郁的日子里感到疲倦
being weary in the days of distress
你的力量就会削弱"
thy strength shall be diminished.
做得好 孩子 非常不错
Fine, my son. Fine.
神父?
Father?
我已经尽力了 真的
I have tried, have I not?
的确 你尽力了
You have, my son.
我已经做到最好了 不错
-I've done my best, have I not? -Indeed.
我从没有干过任何犯法的事
I've never been guilty of any institutional infraction, have I?
你当然没有 655321 你对我帮助很大
You certainly have not, 655321. You've been very helpful.
而且你有改过自新的希望
And you've shown a genuine desire to reform.
神父
Father
能和您单独谈你一个问题吗?
can I ask you a question in private?
当然可以 孩子
Certainly, my son. Certainly.
有什么困扰你吗 我的孩子?
Is there something troubling you, my son?
不要害羞 尽管说
Don't be shy to speak up.
记住
Remember
我知道
I know of the
男青年
urges that can trouble young men
渴求什么
deprived
在与女性社会隔绝的这里
of the society of women.
神父 并不是这样的
It's nothing like that, Father.
是关于他们新的话题
It's about this new thing they're all talking about.
关于新的改造方式
About this new treatment.
那会让你尽快出狱
It gets you out of prison in no time.
也保证你永远不会再进来
And makes sure you never get back in again.
你从哪儿听来的?
Where did you hear about this?
谁讲过这些事?
Who's been talking about these things?
到处都有人讲
These things get around.
狱警也在说 那我想应该是真的了
Two warders talk, as it might be.
而我恰好听到了这些谈话
And somebody can't help overhearing what they say.
有人在车间里找到一张废报纸
Then somebody picks up a scrap of newspaper in the workshops
一切都在报纸上得到了证实
and the newspaper tells all about it.
能让我试试这新方式吗 神父?
How about putting me in for this new treatment, Father?
我想你所指的应该是
I take it you are referring
鲁道维科技术吧?
to the Ludovico technique.
我不知道那叫什么 神父
I don't know what it's called, Father.
我只知道那会让人尽早出狱
All I know is that it gets you out quickly
以及保证他不再入狱
and makes sure you never get back in again.
那还没经过证实 655321
That is not proven, 655321.
事实上 它现在还处于试验阶段
In fact, it is only in the experimental stage at this moment.
已经有人用过了吗?
It has been used, hasn't it?
但在这个监狱还没有
It has not been used in this prison yet.
监狱长不太接受这种技术
The governor has grave doubts about it.
我听说这种技术危险性很大
And I've heard there are very serious dangers involved.
我不怕危险 神父
I don't care about the dangers.
我只想变好
I just want to be good.
我希望以后的生活中
I want for the rest of my life to be
我会变得善良
one act of goodness.
问题在于
The question is
这种技术是否真的能使人变好
whether or not this technique really makes a man good.
善由心生
Goodness comes from within.
善良
Goodness
是由人自己去选择的
is chosen.
当人不能选择的时候
When a man cannot choose
他也不再是人了
he ceases to be a man.
我不懂这些前因后果
I don't understand about the whys and wherefores, Father.
我只知道自己想变好
I only know I want to be good.
耐心点 孩子
Be patient, my son.
相信上帝 他会帮助你
Put your trust in the Lord.
上帝会指引子民 使他们再生
Instruct Thy Son and He shall refresh thee
并且净化他们的灵魂
and shall give delight to thy soul.
阿门
Amen.
部长!所有人已到齐 先生
-Mister! -All present and correct, sir!
好
Right!
所有人已到齐
All present and correct, sir!
犯人们 停
Prisoners, halt!
现在注意了!
Now pay attention!
我要你们分成两行
I want you in two lines
面向这里 背靠墙
up against that wall, facing this way.
来吧 排队
Go on, move!
快点
Hurry up!
不要交头接耳
Stop talking!
先生 犯人已准备好 请检阅
Prisoners ready for inspection, sir!
一间牢房住多少人?
How many to a cell?
在这幢楼里是四个 先生
Four in this block, sir.
把犯人挤到一起我们能得到什么?
Cram criminals together and what do you get?
浓缩的犯罪 服刑期间的犯罪
Concentrated criminality. Crime in the midst of punishment.
是的 先生 可我们需要更大的监狱 更多的钱
I agree, sir. We need larger prisons, more money.
暂时还不能够满足你的要求
Not a chance, my dear fellow.
政府正准备抛弃
The government can't be concerned any longer
过时的受刑规则
with outmoded penalogical theories.
不久 我们的监狱都会人满为患
Soon we may need all prison space for political offenders.
普通罪犯最好采用纯治疗性的方式来改造
Common criminals are best dealt with on a purely curative basis.
把顽固不化的罪犯杀掉 这就是新规则
Kill the criminal reflex, that's all.
这将会在一年内进行推广实施
Full implementation in a year's time.
你们可以看到 惩罚对一些顽固罪犯毫无作用
Punishment means nothing to them. You can see that.
他们甚至享受所谓的惩罚
They enjoy their so-called punishment.
你说得非常对 先生
You're absolutely right, sir.
闭上你的臭嘴
Shut your bleeding hole!
是谁说的?
Who said that?
我 先生
I did, sir.
你犯了什么罪?
What crime did you commit?
过失杀人罪 先生
The accidental killing of a person, sir.
他由于盗窃败露而残忍地杀死女事主
He brutally murdered a woman in furtherance of theft.
他要坐十四年牢 先生
Fourteen years, sir.
很好
Excellent.
他有进取心
He's enterprising
有攻击性
aggressive
有个人主见
outgoing
年轻
young
大胆
bold
邪恶
vicious.
他会变好的
He'll do.
好的
Fine.
我们还可以看看C幢
We could still look at C-block.
不 不 这已足够了 他很适合试验
No, no. That's enough. He's perfect.
我想看他的档案
I want his records sent to me.
这邪恶的小青年
This vicious young hoodlum
将会改头换面
will be transformed out of all recognition.
非常感谢你给我的机会 先生
Thank you very much for this chance, sir.
我们希望你能够成功 孩子
Let's hope you make the most of it, my boy.
请到我的办公室来吧　谢谢!
-Shall we go to my office? -Thank you.
进来吧
Come in.
先生
Sir!
655321已带到!
655321. Sir!
非常好 警官
Very good, Chief.
站到白线后面 脚趾不能越过白线
Over to the line. Toes behind it.
向狱长讲出你的全名和编号
Full name and number to the governor.
亚历山大・德拉吉 先生 编号655321 先生
Alexander DeLarge, sir. 655321, sir.
我认为你并不知道今早那位大人物是谁
I don't suppose you know who that was this morning.
他就是内务部长先生
That was no less a personage than the Minister of the Interior.
新上任的内务部长正准备
The new Minister of the Interior.
大刀阔斧进行改革
What they call a very new broom.
这些可笑的方案最终出台了
These new ridiculous ideas have come at last.
我还是会照章办事
And orders are orders
但在个人而言 我并不赞成
though I may say to you in confidence, I do not approve.
我认为 以牙还牙
An eye for an eye, I say.
如果某人打你 你会还击 对吗?
If someone hits you, you hit back, do you not?
为什么国家被像你这样的
Why should not the state, severely hit by you hooligans
不良少年攻击时也不还手?
not hit back also?
新的看法是绝不还手
The new view is to say " no. "
它着重于把坏人改造为好人
The new view is that we turn the bad into good.
但在我看来 这很不公正
All of which seems to me to be grossly unjust.
我 闭上你的臭嘴
Shut your filthy hole, you scum!
你将会改过自新
You are to be reformed.
明天 你会去见一个名叫布罗德斯基的人
Tomorrow you will go to this man, Brodsky.
你将会离开这里
You will be leaving here.
会被送到鲁道维科医疗中心
You will be transferred to the Ludovico medical facility.
可以相信 你会在两星期内离开国家监狱
It's believed you'll be able to leave state custody in a fortnight.
我觉得这消息会让你很高兴 对吧?
I suppose that prospect pleases you?
回答狱长的话
Answer the governor's question!
一定会的 先生 非常感谢
Yes, sir. Thank you very much.
我在这里已经做得很好了 真的
I've done my best here, I really have, sir.
谢谢大家的关心 先生
I'm very grateful to all concerned, sir.
在这里标记的地方签个名
Sign this where it's marked.
不要看 只管签!
Don't read it, sign it!
上面讲的是你自愿把受刑
It says you're willing to have your sentence commuted
改为鲁道维科治疗方式
to submission to the Ludovico treatment.
还有这张
And this.
还有这张复本
And another copy.
第二天早上 我被带往
The next morning I was taken to
鲁道维科治疗中心
the Ludovico medical facility
它位于市中心外面
outside the town center.
我感到有一点儿伤心
I felt a malenky bit sad
向旧监狱说声再见吧
having to say goodbye to the old Staja
就像离开一个熟悉的地方所做的那样
as you will, when you leave a place you've gotten used to.
好 犯人停下来
Right, halt the prisoner.
早上好 先生 我是监狱警长巴恩斯
Good morning, sir. I'm Chief Officer Barnes.
我把655321号犯人从
I've got 655321
帕尔莫监狱移送到鲁道维科治疗中心
on a transfer from Parkmoor to the Ludovico Centre, sir.
早上好 我们正在等你们
Good morning. Yes, we've been expecting you.
我是阿尔科特医生
I'm Dr. Alcot.
阿尔科特医生
Dr. Alcot.
非常好 先生
Very good, sir.
你准备好接收犯人了吗? 是的 当然
-Are you prepared for the prisoner? -Yes, of course.
请你在这些文件上签个字
I wonder if you'd mind signing these documents, sir.
先生 那儿
There, sir.
还有那儿 先生
And there, sir.
还有这
And there.
请拿好
There you are.
监狱随从 过来
Prison escort, move forward!
停!
Halt!
请原谅 先生
Excuse me, sir.
那位是专门监管他的警官吧?
Is that the officer who will take charge of the prisoner?
提个建议 医生 这家伙可要多加注意
A word of advice, Doc. You'll have to watch this one.
他曾经是一个残暴的混蛋 很有可能还会是
A right brutal bastard he has been, and will be again
不要被他的忏悔和诵经所迷惑
in spite of all his sucking up and reading the Bible.
我们会看好他的 查里 带他到房间吧
We can manage things. Charlie, will you show the young man to his room, now?
是的 先生 请走这边
Right, sir. Come this way, please.
早上好 查理　早上好 医生
-Morning, Charlie. -Good morning, Doctor.
早上好 阿历克斯
Good morning, Alex.
我是布莱诺姆医生 布罗德斯基医生的助手
My name is Dr. Branom. I'm Dr. Brodsky's assistant.
早上好 女士们!天气不错!
Good morning, missus. Lovely day, isn't it?
是的 确实不错
Indeed, it is.
可以拿开吗?
May I take that?
今天早上感觉如何?非常不错
-How are you feeling this morning? -Fine, fine.
好的 你等一会儿要和布罗德斯基医生见面
Good. In a few minutes you'll meet Dr. Brodsky
接着就会开始治疗
and begin your treatment.
你被选中是非常幸运的
You're a very lucky boy to have been chosen.
我知道的 所以我很荣幸
I realize that, and I'm very grateful.
我们将成为朋友 是吗?
We're going to be friends, aren't we?
我希望会 女士
I hope so, missus.
为什么打针?让我睡觉?
What's the hypo for? Sending me to sleep?
你放心 不是麻醉针
Nothing of the sort.
是维他命营养素吗?　差不多
-Vitamins will it be, then? -Something like that.
你营养不足 所以每顿饭后我们都给你打一针
You're undernourished, so after each meal we'll give you a shot.
身子转向右边
Roll over on your right side.
把睡裤拉到半高
Loosen your pajama pants and pull them halfway down.
治疗是怎样进行的?
What exactly is the treatment here going to be, then?
其实 那非常简单
It's quite simple, really.
我们将让你看一些电影
We're going to show you some films.
你的意思是像去电影院一样?
You mean like going to the pictures?
差不多吧
Something like that.
那不错
That's good.
我喜欢不时的看看老片子
I like to viddy the old films now and again.
我爱看电影
And viddy films I would.
兄弟们 我被带到了一个
Where I was taken to, brothers
从没有看过电影的地方
was like no cine I ever viddied before.
我被用紧身衣绑了起来
I was bound up in a straitjacket
并戴上一个
and my gulliver was strapped to a headrest
插满导线的头盔
with wires running away from it.
然后在我眼角夹上了支架
Then they clamped, like, lid-locks on me eyes
于是我的眼睛就不能闭上 无论怎样努力也不行
so that I could not shut them, no matter how hard I tried.
我觉得这有点疯狂
It seemed a bit crazy to me
但我甘愿受他们摆布
but I let them get on with what they wanted to get on with.
如果我能在两星期内重获自由
If I was to be a free malchick again in a fortnight
我甘愿做更多的试验 兄弟们
I would put up with much in the meantime, my brothers.
第一场电影非常棒 镜头拍得很专业
The first film was a very good, professional piece of cine
就像一部好莱坞电影
like it was done in Hollywood.
声音效果非常逼真
The sounds were real horrorshow.
你可以听到尖叫和呻吟非常逼真
You could slooshy the screams and moans very realistic.
你甚至可以听到呼吸声和呻吟声
You could even get the breathing and panting
只是分不清是打人者的还是被打者的
of the tolchocking malchicks at the same time.
那么 从中知道了什么?
And then what do you know?
不久 我们亲爱的老朋友
Soon our dear old friend
红红的 成片的血
the red, red vino on tap
染满了被打者的全身
the same in all places
鲜血渐渐连成一片
like it's put out by the same firm
开始涌出
began to flow.
那真是太美丽了
It was beautiful.
真实世界的颜色是一个有趣的话题
It's funny how the colors of the real world
只是看上去非常真实
only seem really real
当你在看电影的时候
when you viddy them on a screen.
每当我看到达些场景时
Now, all the time I was watching this
我开始有点意识到
I was beginning to get very aware
觉得那样并不好
of, like, not feeling all that well.
这也许是我营养太好的缘故
And this I put down to all the rich food and vitamins.
我尝试不再想了 开始观赏下部片子
But I tried to forget this, concentrating on the next film
出现了一个轮奸的场景
which jumped right away on a young devotchka
一个红发女人在草地上被人轮奸
who was being given the old in-out, in-out
男人上了一个
first by one malchick
又上一个
then another.
接着又一个
Then another.
当轮到第六或第七个男人的时候
When it came to the 6th or 7th malchick
他色迷迷的看着笑着 然后俯下身去
leering and smecking and then going into it
我开始感到想呕吐了
I began to feel really sick.
但我不得不看
But I could not shut me glazzies.
即使稍微转动眼球
And even if I tried to move my glazzballs about
我还是不能摆脱
I still could not get out of
电影中的场景
the line of fire of this picture.
让我起来吧
Get me up.
我想吐了
I'm going to be sick.
快拿东西过来让我吐啊!
Get something for me to be sick in!
很快 药物会使试验者
Very soon now, the drug will cause the subject
感到一种类似死亡的麻痹
to experience a deathlike paralysis
并伴有深刻的恐惧和无助感
together with deep feelings of terror and helplessness.
我们早期的一个试验者曾描述过那感觉就像死了一样
One of our early test subjects described it as being like death.
一种窒息或水淹的感觉
A sense of stifling or drowning.
而在这段时间内 我们发现
And it is during this period, we have found
试验者会把自身遭遇与暴力场面联系起来
the subject will make his most rewarding associations
譬如他的家庭背景 经历 环境等
between his catastrophic experience, environment
暴力场面给他很大的震撼
and the violence he sees.
布罗德斯基医生对你很满意
Dr. Brodsky is pleased with you.
你在治疗中的反应很令人欣喜
You've made a very positive response.
明天将会有两部分 早上和下午
Tomorrow there will be two sessions, morning and afternoon.
你的意思是一天之内看两部?
You mean I have to viddy two sessions in one day?
我觉得你每天看完之后情绪都会有点波动
I imagine you'll feel a bit limp by the end of the day.
但我们必须对你严格要求 你需要治疗
But we have to be hard on you. You have to be cured.
那太可怕了
It was horrible.
的确很可怕
Of course it was horrible.
暴力本身就可怕
Violence is a very horrible thing.
这正是你要学习的
That's what you're learning now.
你的躯体也在学习
Your body's learning it.
我只是不明白为什么想吐
I just don't understand about feeling sick the way I did.
我从来不会呕吐 相反 以前我对这些场景会很喜欢
I never used to feel sick. I used to feel the very opposite.
从前 在干或看的时候我都会很卖力
Doing it or watching it, I used to feel real horrorshow.
你下午感到不适 正是你变好的迹象
You felt ill this afternoon because you're getting better.
正常人对这些暴力场面
When we're healthy, we respond to the hateful
都是持憎恶态度的
with fear and nausea.
你正在恢复正常 仅此而已
You're becoming healthy, that's all.
但明天的这个时候你会比现在更正常
By this time tomorrow, you'll be healthier still.
到了第二天 兄弟们
It was the next day, brothers
我的确表现不错
and I had truly done my best
早上下午的表现
morning and afternoon to play it their way
都中规中矩
and sit like a horrorshow cooperative malchick
当他们变换特级暴力场景的时候
in the chair of torture
我在椅子上活受罪
while they flashed nasty bits of ultra-violence on the screen
尽管没压原本声音 这次听到的全是音乐
though not on the soundtrack, the only sound being music.
然后 我注意到 在痛苦与不适之中
Then I noticed, in all my pain and sickness
那声响像是坠毁声和爆炸声
what music it was that, like, cracked and boomed.
那就像路德维希・凡・贝多芬的音乐
It was Ludwig van.
第九交响曲第四章
Ninth Symphony, fourth movement.
停!停 我求求你
Stop it! Stop it! Please, I beg you!
这是一种罪恶!
It's a sin!
罪恶?
Sin?
罪恶是怎么回事?
What's all this about sin?
就是这个
That!
这样用路德维希・凡的音乐 他没有伤害过谁
Using Ludwig van like that. He did no harm to anyone.
贝多芬只是谱曲
Beethoven just wrote music.
你是不是指背景音乐?
Are you referring to the background score?
你以前听过他吗?
You've heard Beethoven before?
这么说你对音乐很敏感了
So you're keen on music?
无可救药
Can't be helped.
这可能是所谓的罪恶之因吧
Here's the punishment element perhaps.
总督应该很高兴
The governor ought to be pleased.
对不起 阿历克斯
I'm sorry, Alex.
那是为了你好
This is for your own good.
你得忍耐我们一会了
You'll have to bear with us for a while.
但这不公平
But it's not fair. It's not fair I should feel ill
我听到美妙的贝多芬音乐时 怎能感到恶心呢?
when I hear lovely, lovely Ludwig van.
你一定得冒这个险 小子
You must take your chance, boy.
选择是你的
The choice has been all yours.
你不必多说了 先生
You needn't take it any further, sir.
你已经向我证明了极端暴力和杀戮是错的
You've proved to me all this ultra-violence and killing
不对的 绝对错的
is wrong, wrong and terribly wrong!
我已经吸取教训了 先生
I've learned me lesson, sir.
我现在已经看到了我从看到过的
I see now what I've never seen before.
我已经治好了 感谢上帝
I'm cured. Praise God!
你还没被治愈 小子
You're not cured yet, boy.
但先生
But, sirs.
女士
Missus!
我知道错了
I see that it's wrong!
这是错的 因为它反社会
It's wrong because it's, like, against society.
因为人人都有活下去并快乐的权力
Because everybody has the right to live and be happy
而不被打击和刀刺
without being tolchocked and knifed!
不 不 小子 这个还是由我们来做吧
No, no, boy. You really must leave it to us.
但开心一点吧
But be cheerful about it.
不到两星期以后 你就自由了
In less than a fortnight now, you'll be a free man.
女士们 先生们
Ladies and gentlemen
在这里我们介绍实验者本人
at this stage, we introduce the subject himself.
你们已发现他健康而且保养很好
He is, as you will perceive, fit and well-nourished.
他刚刚睡了一个好觉 吃饱了早餐
He comes straight from a night's sleep and a good breakfast
没有吸毒
undrugged
没有被催眠
unhypnotized.
明天我们将满怀信心地将他重新送返世界
Tomorrow we send him out with confidence into the world again
就像你在早晨遇到的小伙子一样
as decent a lad as you would meet on a May morning.
女士们 先生们 改变是巨大的
What a change is here, ladies and gentlemen.
对他进行了惩治
From the hoodlum the state committed
国家在两年前
to unprofitable punishment two years ago.
两年之中他没有改变
Unchanged after two years.
没有改变 不是吗?
Unchanged, do I say?
然而不是这样
Not quite.
监狱教会了他阴险和虚伪的手段
Prison taught him the false smile, the rubbed hands of hypocrisy.
这种诱人 温情的微笑和媚眼
The fawning, greased, obsequious leer.
他也学会了其它罪恶
Other vices it taught him
同时也更加肯定了他以前的恶习
as well as confirming him in those he had long practiced before.
我们党承诺恢复秩序和法律
Our party promised to restore law and order
并将街道变为对常人来说安全的地方
and to make the streets safe for the ordinary peace-loving citizen.
这个承诺现在将要实现
This pledge is now about to become a reality.
女士们 先生们 今天是一个历史性时刻
Ladies and gentlemen, today is an historic moment.
犯罪暴力问题既将成为历史
The problem of criminal violence is soon to be a thing of the past.
但多说无益
But enough of words.
行动胜过一切
Actions speak louder than.
现在就行动
Action now.
各位请看
Observe all.
部长 我们期盼这一天很久了
Our necks are out a long way on this, Minister.
我对布罗德斯基有十足信心
I have complete faith in Brodsky.
如果民意测验正确的话 我们赢定了
If the polls are right, we have nothing to lose.
你好 垃圾
Hello, heap of dirt.
你不常洗澡 不是吗? 从你身上的味道可以闻出
You don't wash much, do you, judging by the horrible smell.
你为什么这么说 我今早刚洗过
Why do you say that? I had a shower this morning.
他今早洗过澡
He had a shower this morning.
你是不是说我在撒谎?
You trying to call me a liar?
不 兄弟
No, brother.
你一定在想我愚蠢至极
You must think I'm awfully stupid.
你为什么这么做 兄弟?
Why did you do that, brother?
我从没有对不起你
I've never done wrong to you.
想知道我为什么这么做吗?
You want to know why I did that?
要知道
Well, you see
我这么做
I do this
也这么做
and that
是因为我不喜欢你这种人 不是吗?
and this because I don't like your horrible type, do I?
如果你想开始干什么的话
And if you want to start something
那就请吧 来吧
you just go ahead. Go on!
请吧
Please do!
我觉得不行了
I'm going to be sick.
不行了吗?
You're going to be sick, are you?
不行了 让我站起来吧
I'm going to be sick. Please let me get up.
你想站起来吗?
You want to get up?
你现在给我听好
Well, now you listen to me.
如果你想站起来的话
If you want to get up
你得为我做件事
you've got to do something for me.
这里
Here.
你看见了吗?
You see that?
你看见这只鞋吗?
You see that shoe?
我要你舔它
I want you to lick it.
继续
Go on!
舔它
Lick it!
我的兄弟们 你们相不相信
And, my brothers, would you believe
你真正的朋友 这个饱受折磨的讲述者
your faithful friend and long-suffering narrator
把他的红舌头伸出了一里半
pushed out his red yabzick a mile and a half
去舔这只脏靴子
to lick the grahzny, vonny boots.
再来一次
And again!
痛不欲生的恶心感又一次出现了
The horrible killing sickness had whooshed up
将打斗的快乐
and turned the joy of battle
转变为我不屑一顾的感觉
into a feeling I was going to snuff it.
再来一次
And again.
好极了 很干净
Nice and clean.
非常感谢你
Thank you very much.
这非常好
That will do very well.
非常感谢 女士们 先生们
Thank you very much, ladies and gentlemen.
她走向我
She came towards me
照在她身上的光就像上帝的光芒
with the light, like it was the light of heavenly grace.
进入我脑海的东西
And the thing that flashed in me gulliver
是让她躺在地板上
was that I'd like to have her there on the floor
干老一套 疯狂的干
with the old in-out, real savage.
但恶心感飞快的袭来
But quick as a shot came the sickness.
就像在街角监视的侦探一样
Like a detective who'd been watching around the corner
现在现身来逮捕我
and now followed to make his arrest.
够了
Enough!
非常感谢
Thank you very much.
谢谢 亲爱的
Thank you, my dear.
你现在感觉好点了吗?
Not feeling too bad now, are you?
不 先生 我觉得好极了
No, sir. I feel really great, sir.
好 还可以吗 先生?
-Good. -Was it all right, sir?
我做的好吗?
Did I do well?
很好 孩子 好极了
Fine, my boy. Absolutely fine.
你们看到了 女士们 先生们
You see, ladies and gentlemen
我们的实验者被驱使做善事
our subject is impelled towards the good
同时也矛盾地被驱使做恶
by paradoxically being impelled towards evil.
暴力的企图
The intention to act violently
被身体的不适伴随
is accompanied by strong feelings of physical distress.
为了抵消这个实验者必须转向
To counter these, the subject has to switch
一种截然不同的态度
to a diametrically opposed attitude.
有问题吗?
Any questions?
选择
Choice!
这孩子没有真正的选择 不是吗?
The boy has no real choice, has he?
自我利益
Self-interest.
对生理疼痛的害怕
The fear of physical pain
驱使他进行古怪的自虐行为
drove him to that grotesque act of self-abasement.
这个做法很明显缺乏诚意
Its insincerity was clearly to be seen.
他不再是一个犯错者了
He ceases to be a wrongdoer.
也不是一个能做道德选择的生灵了
He ceases also to be a creature capable of moral choice.
帕德 这些很难说
Padre, these are subtleties.
我们不关心动机 也不关心更高的道德规范
We're not concerned with motives, with the higher ethics.
我们只关心打击犯罪
We are concerned only with cutting down crime.
为了缓解监狱里的拥挤状况
And with relieving the ghastly congestion in our prisons.
他将成为一个真正的基督敦徒
He will be your true Christian
甘愿受罚
ready to turn the other cheek.
甘愿受难 而不是让别人受难
Ready to be crucified, rather than crucify.
连杀一只苍蝇也会心痛
Sick to the very heart at the thought even of killing a fly.
解救
Reclamation.
上帝的天使般的欢乐
Joy before the angels of God.
关键是它非常有效
The point is that it works!
第二天 你的朋友 谦卑的讲述者
And the very next day, your friend and humble narrator
终获自由
was a free man.
我想嫁一个守灯塔的 让他给我做伴
I wanna marry a lighthouse keeper and keep him company.
我想嫁个守灯塔的 伴着海边的景色生活
I want to marry a lighthouse keeper and live by the sight of the sea.
我会在阳光下擦亮灯 给夜航的船只指明路
I'll polish his lamp by the light of day, so ships at night can find their way.
我想嫁一个守灯塔的 那不好吗?
I wanna marry a lighthouse keeper and won't that be OK?
我们会在珊瑚礁上开派对 在海滩上举行野餐
We'll have parties on the coral reef and clambakes on the shore.
我们会邀请邻居来 几十只海鸥
We'll invite the neighbors in, seagulls by the score.
亲爱的 我每天都梦想着住在灯塔里
I dream of live in a lighthouse baby every single day.
儿子
Son!
嗨 爸爸妈妈
Hi, hi, hi there, my Pee and Em.
妈妈
Mum.
亲爱的 你好吗?很高兴见到你
How are you, love? Nice to see you.
爸爸 孩子 真令人惊讶
-Dad. -Lad. What a surprise.
很高兴见到　身体还好吧?
-Good to see you. -Keeping fit?
你怎么样?
How are you, then?
我很好 很好
I'm fine, fine.
没什么麻烦 你知道
Keeping out of trouble, you know.
我回来了
I'm back!
很高兴见到你
Good to see you.
你为什么不让我们知道在发生什么?
Why didn't you let us know what was happening?
我想要给爸爸和你一个惊喜
I wanted it to be, like, a big surprise for you and Pee.
确实是一个惊喜 只是有一点令人措手不及
It's a surprise, all right. A bit bewildering too.
我们刚刚在早报上读到它
We've only just read about it in morning papers.
你应该早让我们知道 孩子
You should have let us know, lad.
不是我们不高兴见到你 而且
Not that we're not very pleased to see you again, and all
治好了吗?全部?
cured too, eh?
对了 他们对我帮助很大
That's right. They did a great job on me.
我完全改变了
I'm completely reformed.
还是老地方吗?
Still the same old place, then?
沙发上坐着一个奇怪的人
There's a strange fellow sitting on the sofa
大口吃着吐司条
munchy-wunching lomticks of toast.
这是乔
That's Joe.
他现在住这里
He lives here now.
寄宿的
The lodger.
他是一个寄宿的
That's what he is.
他租了你的房间
He rents your room.
乔 你好
How do you do, Joe?
房间还舒服吧
Find the room comfortable, do you?
没什么抱怨?
No complaints?
我听说过你
I've heard about you.
我知道你干了什么
I know what you've done.
也伤透了你可怜的父母的心
Breaking the hearts of your poor, grieving parents.
现在你回来了
So you're back, eh?
再一次让你父母的生活变得悲惨?
Back to make life a misery for your lovely parents once more?
除非把我杀了 否则别想
Over my dead corpse, you will.
你知道他们对待我像自己的儿子一样
Because, you see, they've let me be more like a son to them
而不是一个寄宿者
than like a lodger.
不要在这里打了 孩子们
Don't go fighting here, boys.
请用手盖住你的嘴
Do put your hand over your mouth, please.
这样抽搐很恶心
It's bloody revolting.
你没事吧?
Are you all right?
这是治疗的效果
It's the treatment.
很恶心 足够让你把食物都吐出来
It's disgusting. Enough to put you off your food.
别理他 乔 这是治疗的效果
Leave him be, Joe. It's the treatment.
你认为我们该做点什么吗?
Do you think we ought to do something?
你要一杯茶吗 儿子?
Would you like me to make you a nice cup of tea, son?
你把我的私人东西怎么处置了?
What have you done with all me own personal things?
它们全被
That was all
拿走了 儿子
took away, son.
警察拿走的
By the police.
新规定 明白
New regulation, see
是对受害者的补偿
about compensation for the victims.
巴斯尔怎么样了
What about Basil?
我的蛇在哪里?
Where is my snake?
它好像遇到了
He met with
一场事故
like, an accident.
它死了
He passed away.
那我又将会怎么样呢?
What's going to happen to me, then?
我是说
I mean
他进的是我的屋
that's my room he's in.
不可否认这一点
There's no denying that.
这也是我的家
This is my home also.
爸爸妈妈 你们有什么建议?
What suggestions have you, my Pee and Em, to make?
这需要考虑 儿子
All this needs thinking about, son.
我们不能一下子把乔赶走
We can't very well just kick Joe out.
不能那样做
Not just like that, can we?
我是说
I mean
乔在这里有工作做
Joe's here doing a job.
实际上是一个合约 两年期
A contract it is. Two years.
我们做了安排 不是吗 乔?
We made, like, an arrangement. Didn't we, Joe?
你要知道 儿子
You see, son
乔已经付了下个月房租
Joe's paid next month's rent already
不论未来我们做什么 我们不能只是说
so whatever we may do in the future, we can't just say
让他离开 不是吗?
to Joe to get out, now can we?
不 不止这个
No, but it's much more than that.
我是说 你们两个让我想起
I mean, I've got you two to think of
谁像父母一样对待我
who've been like a father and mother to me.
我离开这里和你们两个是不对的
It wouldn't be right for me to go off and leave you two
而让你们被这个怪物怜悯
to the tender mercies of this young monster
他一点也不像真正的儿子
who's been like no real son at all.
看 他在哭
Look, he's weeping now.
但这正是他狡猾技俩
But that's all his craft and artfulness.
让他走到别处找地方住
Let him go and find a room somewhere else.
让他自食其果 知道一个坏孩子
Let him learn the errors of his way, and that a bad boy
像他这样是不配有你们这样的好父母的
doesn't deserve such a good mum and dad as he's had.
好吧
All right.
我知道情况了
I know how things are now.
我受了那么多罪
I've suffered and I've suffered
不断受罪
and I've suffered.
每个人都想让我不断受罪
And everybody wants me to go on suffering.
你让别人受罪
You've made others suffer.
你受罪是应该的
It's only right that you should suffer proper.
别人告诉了我你做的一切
I've been told everything you've done
晚上围坐在桌旁
sitting around the family table.
听上去令人震惊
And pretty shocking it was to listen to.
其中许多令我作呕
It made me real sick, a lot of it did.
现在看看你母亲做了什么
Now look what you've gone and done to your mother.
别哭了 现在没事了
Come on. It's all right now.
好吧
Right!
我现在就走
I'm leaving now.
你们再也不用见我了
You won't ever viddy me no more.
我自己靠自己
I'll make me own way.
非常感谢你 你们要对得起自己的良心
Thank you very much. Let it lie heavy on your consciences.
别那么想 儿子
Now don't take it like that, son.
给点钱吧 兄弟
Can you spare some cutter, me brother?
谢谢 老兄
Thanks, brother.
坚尼 麦克
Jamey! Mack!
愿天使
May the hokey fly!
圣母和上帝保佑我们
Mother of God and all the blessed saints in heaven preserve us!
我从不忘记别人的样子 上帝啊!
I never forget a face, me God!
我从不忘记别人的样子
I never forget any face.
离开我 老兄 我从未见过你
Leave me alone, brother. I've never seen you before!
这就是差点干掉我的那个年轻混蛋
This is the poisonous young swine that near done me in.
他和他的朋友
Him and his friends.
他们打我 踢我 刺我
They beat me and kicked me and punched me.
抓住他 抓住他
Stop him! Stop him!
这条恶狗 他们看着我呻吟却哈哈大笑
They laughed at me blood and me moans, this murderous dog!
接着便是一群肮脏的老头子一拥而上
Then there was like a sea of dirty, smelly old men
用他们苍老无力的手
trying to get at your humble narrator
试图抓住我
with their feeble rookers and horny old claws.
老家伙在教训年轻人
It was old age having a go at youth.
我什么也不敢做 我的兄弟
And I daren't do a single solitary thing, my brothers.
那样挨打更好
It being better to be hit at like that
也不要恶心 感觉到那可怕的疼痛
than want to sick and feel that horrible pain.
好了 好了
All right, all right!
现在住手
Stop it now!
好了 不要扰乱治安 你们这些捣蛋鬼
Come on. Stop breaking the state's peace, you naughty boys!
退后 走吧
Back away! Go away with you!
你有什么麻烦吗?先生?
What's your trouble, sir?
噢 不
Oh, no!
天哪!
Well!
天哪! 天哪! 天哪!
Well, well, well!
如果这不是小阿历克斯就怪了
If it isn't little Alex.
好久不见 老兄
Long time no viddy, droog.
怎么样?
How goes?
这不可能
It's impossible.
我不相信
I don't believe it.
说话的证据
Evidence of the old glazzies.
我们什么也没骗你
Nothing up our sleeves.
阿历克斯 不是巧合
No magic, little Alex.
只是两个到工作年龄的人找的工作罢了
A job for two who are now of job age.
当警察
The police.
过来 阿历克斯
Come on, Alex.
下来走走
Come for walking.
来来来吧 伙计们
Come, come, come, my little droogies.
我一点也不明白
I just don't get this at all.
过去的日子一去不返了
The old days are dead and gone.
但我已为过去所做的受过惩罚了
For what I did in the past, I've been punished.
我已经被治好了
I've been cured.
检查官已经告诉了我们一切
That was read out to us.
检查官宣读这一切给我们。
The inspector read it all out to us.
他说这是一种很好的方法
He said it was a very good way.
那这些是在干什么?
But what is all this?
是他们抓住我的 兄弟
It was them that went for me, brothers.
你不是他们一边的 不可能是
You're not on their side, and can't be.
蒂姆 你不会是的
You can't be, Dim.
那是我们过去曾经戏弄过的人
It was someone we fillied with back in the old days
现在要复仇了 记得吗?
trying to get his own revenge after all this time. Remember?
是很长时间
A long time is right.
我不记得那些日子了 太可怕了
I don't remember them days too horrorshow.
也不要再喊我"蒂姆"了
And don't call me Dim no more, either.
称我为"警官"
Officer, call me.
你记得足够了 阿历克斯
Enough is remembered, though, little Alex.
这是为了确保你能被治愈
And this is to make sure you stay cured.
够了
That's enough.
再打几下 他还在乱踢
A bit more. He's still kicking.
治好了 是吗?
Cured, are you?
下次再见 伙计
Be viddying you some more sometime, droogie.
我该去哪里?没钱也没家
Where was I to go, who had no home and no money?
我为自己哭泣
I cried for meself.
家 家 家
Home, home, home.
我要一个家
It was home I was wanting.
我也到了一个家
And it was home I came to, brothers
我在当时的状态下没意识到
not realizing, in the state I was in
我在哪里和以前曾经到过那里
where I was and had been before.
见鬼 那究竟是谁?
Who on earth could that be?
我来看看是谁
I'll see who it is.
是谁?
Yes, what is it?
请帮个忙
Please
弗兰克 我想这个年轻人需要帮助
Frank, I think this young man needs some help.
我的上帝
My God!
我的孩子 你怎么了?
What's happened to you, my boy?
你能相信吗?朋友 我的兄弟?
And would you believe it, O my brothers and only friends
你的自述人就在这里
there was your faithful narrator
像一个无助的婴儿一样被抱着
being held helpless like a babe in arms
突然意识到他在哪里
and suddenly realizing where he was
为什么门上的"家"是那么的熟悉
and why "home" on the gate had looked so familiar.
但我知道这里是安全的
But I knew I was safe.
我知道他不会记得我
I knew he would not remember me.
因为在那些无忧无虑的日子里
For in those carefree days
我和我所谓的兄弟
I and my so-called droogs
戴着面具 像真的伪装一样
wore our maskies, which were like real horrorshow disguises.
是警察
Police.
可恶的警察
Ghastly, horrible police
他们打我 先生
they beat me up, sir.
警察殴打我 先生
The police beat me up.
我认识你
I know you!
报纸上的照片不是你吗?
Isn't it your picture in the newspapers?
我今早在录像上见到了你
Didn't I see you on the video this morning?
可怕的新技术 你不是那可怜的受害者吗?
Are you not the poor victim of this horrible new technique?
是的 先生
Yes, sir.
那正是我 先生 我是一个受害者 先生
That's exactly who I am and what I am, sir. A victim.
上帝啊 你来这是天意!
Then, by God, you've been sent here by providence!
在监狱里受折磨 还要受警察的折磨
Tortured in prison, then tortured by the police.
我完全为了你 你还不是第一个来这的
My heart goes out to you. You're not the first to come here.
警察们喜欢把他们的犯人带到这个村子来
The police like to bring their victims to this village.
但你的天意在于
But it's providential that you
你作为另一种受害者 来到这里
who are also another kind of victim, should come here.
但你是冷得浑身发抖
But you're cold and shivering.
朱利安
Julian
为年轻人准备洗澡水
draw a bath for this young man.
当然了 法兰克
Certainly, Frank.
非常感谢 先生
Thank you very much, sir.
上帝保佑你 先生
God bless you, sir.
我在雨中歌唱
I'm singing in the rain
在雨中歌唱
Just singing in the rain
要想确保现政府在大选中不回来
He can be the most potent weapon imaginable
他是现在可以想象的最有力的武器
to ensure the government is not returned in the election.
政府最大的吹嘘 先生
The government's big boast, sir
就是他们处理犯罪的方法
is the way they have dealt with crime:
雇佣年轻的暴徒当警察
Recruiting young roughs into the police
提议这样的洗脑技术
proposing will-sapping techniques of conditioning.
以前我们在其它国家看到过
We've seen it before in other countries.
这正是他们忽视的 而对我们很有意义
The thin end of the wedge.
我们因此有了极权主义的全部证据
Before we know it, we'll have the full apparatus of totalitarianism.
这个年青人是这些残暴提议的活见证
This young boy is a living witness to these diabolical proposals.
人民 普通民众 必须知道 必须看到
The people, the common people, must know, must see.
我们有需要捍卫的自由传统
There are traditions of liberty to defend. That tradition is all.
普通民众会听之任之 是的
The common people will let it go, yes.
他们会出卖自由换取安宁的生活
They'll sell liberty for a quieter life.
所以他们需要有人领导
That is why they must be led.
驱使 推动
Driven. Pushed.
好
Fine.
非常谢谢 先生
Thank you very much, sir.
他会来的
He'll be here.
我在雨中歌唱
I'm singing in the rain
在雨中歌唱
Just singing in the rain
多爽的感觉
What a glorious feeling
我又高高高兴起来了
I'm hap-hap-happy again
我在云中大笑
I'm laughing at clouds
上面是多么的黑
So dark up above
太阳在我心中
The sun's in my heart
我已准备去爱
I'm ready for love
让乌黑的云去追逐
Let the stormy clouds chase
它下面每一个人
Everyone from the place
雨尽情地下吧 我面带微笑
Come on with the rain I've a smile on my face
我走在大路上
I'll walk down the lane
有一副幸福的面容
With a happy refrain
我在唱 在
And I'm singing
晚上好 先生
Good evening, sir.
晚上好
Good evening.
谢谢你给我留了这些
It was very kind of you to leave this out for me.
周围没人 所以我就开始吃了
There was no one around, so I started.
这样可以吧 先生?
Hope that's all right, sir.
当然
Of course.
好吃吗?
Food all right?
很好 先生 很好
Great, sir. Great.
尝尝酒
Try the wine.
谢谢
Thank you, sir.
干杯
Cheers.
祝你快乐
Happy days.
要一起来吗
Won't you join me?
不 我的健康不允许
No. My health doesn't allow it.
不 谢了
No, thank you.
1960年的沙图酒
"1960, Chateau
圣埃特州
Saint-Estephe.
梅多卡出的
Medoc."
很好的牌子 先生
Very good brand, sir.
很好的
Very good
颜色 先生
color, sir.
闻起来也很香
Smells nice too.
真的太棒了
Very nice little number.
干了这杯
Here's to it.
真的不赖 先生 真的
Very refreshing, sir. Very refreshing.
我很高兴你喜欢这好酒
I'm pleased you appreciate good wine.
再来一杯
Have another glass.
谢谢
Thanks
我老婆
My wife
曾经为我做好一切而让我专心写作
used to do everything for me and leave me to my writing.
你妻子 先生?她走了?
Your wife? Is she away?
不 她死了
She's dead!
我很遗憾 先生
I'm sorry to hear about that, sir.
她是被轮奸而死了
She was very badly raped, you see.
我们被年轻的坏流氓袭击
We were assaulted by vicious young hoodlums
就在你现在所坐的这个房间里
in this very room you're sitting in now.
我留下了严重的残疾 但她的痛苦太深重了
I was left a helpless cripple, but for her the agony was too great.
医生说她死于肺炎
The doctors said it was pneumonia
因为当时正是流感流行
because it happened later, during a flu epidemic.
医生说是肺炎 但我知道究竟怎么回事
The doctors told me it was pneumonia, but I knew what it was.
现在这个时代的牺牲品 可怜的姑娘!
A victim of the modern age. Poor, poor girl!
现在你是
And now you.
这个时代的另一个受害者
Another victim of the modern age.
但我们可以帮助你
But you can be helped.
刚才你洗澡时 我打了电话给朋友
I phoned some friends while you were having your bath.
一些
Some
朋友?
friends?
是的 他们想帮你
Yes. They want to help you.
帮我 先生?帮你
-Help me? -Help you.
他们是谁?非常重要的人物
-Who are they? -Very, very important people.
他们对你有兴趣
And they're interested in you.
朱利安 一定是他们来了
Julian. This'll be these people now.
我不要想再麻烦你了 我要走了
I don't want to trouble you any further. I should be leaving.
不要走
No no no,my boy
没有问题的
No trouble at all.
来
Here.
我再给你倒一杯
Let me fill your glass.
就是他了
So this is the young man.
你好
How do you do, sir?
很高兴见到你
Missus. I'm very pleased to meet you.
这么晚来打扰你 我希望你能见谅
I hope you forgive us for coming at this hour
我们听说你有些麻烦
but we heard you were in trouble
所以过来看看能否帮些忙
and so we came over to see if we could help.
谢谢你们关心
Very kind of you, sir. Thank you very much.
我知道你
I understand you had a rather
不幸
unfortunate
遭遇了
encounter
警察今天晚上
with the police tonight.
对 我想你可以这么说
Yes, I suppose you could call it that.
现在怎么样?
How are you feeling now?
好多了 谢谢
Much better, thank you.
可以问你几个问题吗?
Feel like talking, answering a few questions?
好的 先生 好的
Fine, sir. Fine.
如我刚才所说 我们听过你的情况
As I said, we've heard about you.
对你的情况很感兴趣
We are interested in your case.
我们想帮你 非常感谢 先生
-We want to help you. -Thank you very much, sir.
可以开始了吗?
Shall we get down to it?
好的 可以 先生
Fine. Fine, sir.
从报纸上写的看
The newspapers mentioned
除了被改造成不能接受性和暴力活动
in addition to being conditioned against acts of sex and violence
你还被无意中改造成不能接受音乐
you've inadvertently been conditioned against music.
我想这是他们没有料到的
I think that was something that they didn't plan for.
你知道吗 女士
You see, missus
我非常喜欢音乐
I'm very fond of music.
特别是贝多芬
Especially Beethoven.
路德维希・凡・贝多芬
Ludwig van Beethoven.
B-E 行了 谢谢
-B-E- -All right, thank you.
只是恰好有一次他们给我
And it just so happened that while they were showing me
放一个坏电影 好像是关于一个集中营的
a particularly bad film of, like, a concentration camp
背景音乐都是贝多芬的
the background music was playing Beethoven.
所以你现在对音乐的反应
So now you have the same reaction to music
就和你对性和暴力一样?
as you do to sex and violence?
不 女士 并不是所有音乐 只是贝九
No, missus. You see, it's not all music. It's just the Ninth.
你是说贝多芬的第九交响曲?
You mean Beethoven's Ninth Symphony?
对 我再不能听第九交响曲了
That's right. I can't listen to the Ninth anymore at all.
当我听见这音乐
When I hear the Ninth, I get, like
我就会有这种奇怪的感觉
this funny feeling.
然后我只想到 就像 要去了结
And then all I can think about is, like, trying to snuff it.
再说一遍 了结 就是去死
-I beg your pardon? -Snuff it. Death, I mean.
我是想平静地
I just want to die peacefully
无痛苦地死去
like, with no pain.
你现在这样想吗?
Do you feel that way now?
不 先生 不怎么想
No, sir, not exactly.
我还是觉得
I still feel
我很惨
very miserable.
情绪非常低落
Very much down in spirits.
你还想
Do you still feel
自杀吗?
suicidal?
嗯 这么说吧
Well. Put it this way:
我感到自己很消沉
I feel very low in myself.
我觉得前途渺茫
I can't see much in the future.
我觉得每一秒钟我都会遇到可怕的事
I feel that any second, something terrible is going to happen to me.
好样的 法兰克
Well done, Frank.
朱利安 请去开车
Julian, get the car, would you, please?
我醒了
I woke up
疼痛遍及了 我的全身
the pain and sickness all over me like an animal.
我明白了
Then I realized what it was.
使我疼痛的便是楼下传来的音乐
The music coming up from the floor
我的老朋友 贝多芬
was our old friend, Ludwig van
和可怕的第九交响曲
and the dreaded Ninth Symphony.
让我出去
Let me out!
打开门
Open the door!
快点 打开门!
Come on, open the door!
关掉
Turn it off!
停止
Stop it!
关掉
Turn it off!
求
Please!
你们关掉
Turn it off!
突然间 我明白了我必须做的
Suddenly, I viddied what I had to do
而且也是我一直想要做的
and what I had wanted to do.
那就是结果了我自己
And that was to do myself in.
了结
To snuff it.
从这个邪恶残酷的世界上彻底消失
To blast off forever, out of this wicked, cruel world.
也许有一时的痛苦
One moment of pain, perhaps
然后就是永远的睡眠
and then sleep.
真的会
Forever and ever
直到永远
and ever.
我跳了 噢我的兄弟们
I jumped, O my brothers
摔得很重
and I fell hard.
但我没有了结
But I did not snuff it.
如果我了结了
If I had snuffed it
我就不会在这讲述我的故事了
I would not be here to tell what I have told.
我重新活了过来 经过了很长很长的黑暗
I came back to life after a long, black, black gap
好像有一百万年
of what might have been a million years.
他苏醒了 大夫
He's recovered consciousness, Doctor.
政府被控在犯罪改革中使用非人道手段
部长被指控非人道疗法
政府是凶手 医生被控 而阿历克斯康复
犯罪疗法男孩引起轩然大波 医生责备政府科学家"改变阿历克斯本性"
阿历克斯试图自杀 洗脑专家受到指责部长遭到谴责
你好 宝贝
Hello, lad.
你好 儿子
Hello, son.
你好吗?
How are you?
好点了吗?
You feeling better?
哪阵风
What
把
gives
我的爹娘吹来了?
My father and mother blowing it?
你们
What makes
以为
you think
自己受欢迎吗?
you are welcome?
好了 不要伤心了
There, there, Mother. It's all right.
他不是有意的
He doesn't mean it.
你又上报了 儿子
You were in the papers again, son.
报上说
It said
他们冤枉你了
they had done great wrong to you.
他们还说了
It said
政府是如何地迫使你尝试
how the government
直到真的
drove you to try
自杀
and do yourself in.
当你再次想起 儿子
And when you think about it, son
我们也有错
maybe it was our fault too
在某些方面
in a way.
该说的说了 该做也做了之后
Your home's your home
你的家还是你的家 儿子
when all's said and done, son.
早上好　早上好 大夫
-Good morning. -Good morning, Doctor.
今天怎么样? 好点了
-How are you feeling today? -Fine, fine.
好 我可以吗?
Good. May I?
我是泰勒医生 以前没见过
-I'm Dr. Taylor. -Haven't seen you before.
我是你的心理医生
I'm your psychiatrist.
心理医生!我需要心理医生吗?
Psychiatrist! Do I need one?
只是医疗程序的一部分而已
Just part of hospital routine.
我们要谈性生活吗?
Are we going to talk about me sex life?
我给你看些幻灯片
I'm going to show you some slides
你要谈你的想法 好吗?
and you're going to tell me what you think about them.
很好
Jolly good.
你了解梦吗?
You know anything about dreams?
一点点
Something, yes.
你知道它们什么意思吗? 可能吧
-You know what they mean? -Perhaps.
你在想什么事吗?
You concerned about something?
不 没什么特别的
No, not concerned, really
只是近来经常做一个怪梦
but I've been having this nasty dream.
很可怕
Very nasty.
好像自己被碾碎
It's like
当我粉碎了一切，你知道
when I was all smashed up, you know
而且好像半是清醒半是昏迷
and half-awake and unconscious-like
近来总做这个梦
I kept having this dream.
所有这些医生都在玩我的脑袋
All these doctors were playing around with me gulliver.
你看 就像我脑子里面
You know, like the inside of me brain.
好像老是反复做这个梦
I seem to have this dream over and over again.
你觉得它意味着什么吗?
Do you think it means anything?
像你这样爱重伤的病人通常会有这样的梦
Patients with injuries like yours often have dreams of this sort.
这只是康复过程的一部分
It's all part of the recovery process.
那么现在 你根据画面中人物
Now then, each of these slides needs a reply
来逐一描述这些幻灯
from one of the people in the picture.
你告诉我你觉得里面的人会说什么
You tell me what you think the person would say
好吗?
all right?
好
Righty-right.
"这羽毛多漂亮啊!"
" Isn't the plumage beautiful? "
我只是说另一个人会说什么吗?
I just say what the other person would say?
别想太久
Don't think about it too long.
说出你意识中首先闪现的东西
Say the first thing that pops into your mind.
卷心菜 灯笼裤
Cabbages. Knickers.
它没有嘴
It's not got a beak.
好
Good.
"你经常和他争吵的男孩病得很厉害"
"The boy you always quarreled with is seriously ill. "
我的意识一片空白
My mind is a blank
我来替你打烂你的脸 孬种
and I'll smash your face for you, yarblockos.
好
Good.
"你想干什么?"
"What do you want? "
我现在没时间 亲爱的 我只是来看表的
No time for the old in-out, love. I've just come to read the meter.
好
Good.
"你卖了我一块坏的表 我要退钱"
"You sold me a crummy watch. I want my money back. "
你知道你能拿那表干什么吗? 粘在你的屁股上
You know what you can do with that watch? Stick it up your ass!
好
Good.
"你可以随便处置它们"
"You can do whatever you like with these. "
蛋
Eggiwegs.
我喜欢把它们
I would like
打碎
to smash them.
然后把它们捡起来
And pick them all up
再扔
and throw--
妈的
Fucking hell!
好了 就这些
There. That's all there is to it.
你没事吧?
Are you all right?
希望吧
Hope so.
完了吗? 是的 我很喜欢
-Is that the end, then? -Yes. -I was quite enjoying that.
那很好
Good. I'm glad.
我做对了多少?
How many did I get right?
这不是那种测验
It's not that kind of a test.
但你的表现说明你会完全康复
But you seem well on the way to making a complete recovery.
那么我什么时候可以出去?
When do I get out, then?
我肯定不会太久了
I'm sure it won't be long now.
所以我等着
So I waited
噢 我的兄弟们
and, O my brothers
我一天天地康复
I got a lot better
大口吃着鸡蛋和大面包
munching away at eggiwegs and lomticks of toast
还有可爱的牛排
and lovely steakie-wakes.
然后有一天
And then one day
他们说我会有一个非常特殊的客人
they said I was going to have a very special visitor.
在外面等一下 好吗 警官? 好的 先生
-Just wait outside for a moment, would you, Officer? -Yes, sir.
恐怕我变动日程影响了你
I'm afraid my change of schedule has thrown you.
病人好像正在吃晚饭
The patient's in the middle of supper.
没关系 部长 这没什么
That's quite all right, Minister. No trouble at all.
晚上好 孩子  嗨 小兄弟们
-Good evening, my boy. -Hi there, my little droogies.
怎么样 年轻人?
How are you getting on, young man?
很好 先生 确实很好
Great, sir. Just great.
还有什么需要我做的吗?
Can I do anything more for you?
没有了 莱斯利先生 非常感谢!
I don't think so, Sir Leslie. Thank you very much.
那么我走了 护士!
Then I leave you to it. Nurse!
你好像一个人占了整个病房 孩子
You seem to have a whole ward to yourself, my boy.
是的 先生
Yes, sir.
不过当我半夜疼醒的时候
And a very lonely place it is too, sir
这里也很孤独 先生
when I wake up in the mid of night with me pain.
很高兴见你逐渐康复
Yes. Well, anyway, good to see you on the mend.
当然我一直和医院保持着联系
I kept in touch with the hospital, of course.
现在我亲自来看你
And now I've come down personally
来看看你过得怎样
to see how you're getting along.
我忍受了非人的折磨
I've suffered the tortures of the damned.
非人的折磨
Tortures of the damned.
是的 我可以理解 你经历了非常
Yes, I can appreciate that you've had an extremely--
让我来帮你 可以吗?
Oh, look. Let me help you with that, shall I?
谢了 先生 谢谢
Thank you, sir. Thank you!
我诚恳地告诉你 作为政府一员的我、以及政府
I can tell you with all sincerity that I and the government of which I'm a member
对此深感歉意 孩子 深感歉意
are deeply sorry about this, my boy. Deeply sorry.
我们尽力来帮助你
We tried to help you.
我们采纳了一些实际上不对的建议
We followed recommendations which were made to us that turned out to be wrong.
调查后会追究责任
An inquiry will place the responsibility where it belongs.
我们想让你把我们当作朋友
We want you to regard us as friends.
我们让你恢复正常
We put you right.
你正在接受最好的治疗
You're getting the best of treatment.
我们从没想让你受伤害
We never wished you harm.
但确实有些人这么想 并且一直这么想
But there are some who did, and do.
而我觉得你知道他们是谁
And I think you know who those are.
有一些人想利用你达到他们的政治目的
There are certain people who wanted to use you for political ends.
你要是死了他们就真高兴了
They would have been glad to have you dead
因为他们那样就可以以此指责政府了
for they thought they could then blame it all on the government.
还有某一个人
There is also a certain man
一个颠覆文学作家
a writer of subversive literature
他一直为你的血而嚎叫
who has been howling for your blood.
他想捅你一刀都想疯了
He's been mad with desire to stick a knife into you.
不过你现在远离他 很安全
But you're safe from him now.
我们把他安置好了
We put him away.
他发现你曾害过他
He found out that you had done wrong to him.
至少他认为你害过他
At least he believed you had done wrong.
他在头脑里形成这样一个念头
He formed this idea in his head that you had been responsible
他一个亲近的人死了 你应该负责
for the death of someone near and dear to him.
他是个危险人物
He was a menace.
我们把他安置好是为保护他自身
We put him away for his own protection.
也为保住你
And also for yours.
他现在在哪 先生?
Where is he now, sir?
我们把他放在不能伤害你的地方
We put him away where he can do you no harm.
你看 我们在关心你的利益
You see, we are looking after your interests.
我们对你感兴趣
We are interested in you.
等你离开你会无忧无虑 我们会安排好一切
When you leave here, you'll have no worries. We'll see to everything.
一份好工作 待遇也不错
A good job on a good salary.
什么工作 多少钱?
What job and how much?
你将会有份有趣的工作 待遇也会让你满足
You'll have an interesting job at a salary which you would regard as adequate.
不仅是为你将去做的工作
Not only for the job you're going to do
也为了补偿你认为你所忍受的痛苦
and in compensation for what you believe you have suffered
还因为你在帮助我们
but also because you are helping us.
帮助你们 先生?
Helping you, sir?
我们总是帮助我们的朋友 不是吗?
We always help our friends, don't we?
现政府因为你而失去不少支持
It is no secret that this government
这已不是秘密 我的孩子
has lost a lot of popularity because of you, my boy.
有些人认为下次竞选我们会下台
There are some who think that at the next election we shall be out.
对于我们的努力尝试
The press has chosen to take a very unfavorable view
媒体采取了很不利的观点
of what we tried to do.
但公众观点有办法转变
But public opinion has a way of changing.
而你 阿历克斯
And you, Alex
如果我可以叫你阿历克斯
if I may call you Alex
当然 先生 他们在家怎样叫你?
Certainly, sir. What do they call you at home?
我名叫弗雷德里克
My name is Frederick.
如我所说 阿历克斯
As I was saying, Alex
你将有助于改变公众的判断
you can be instrumental in changing the public's verdict.
你明白吗 阿历克斯?
Do you understand, Alex?
我说清楚了吗?
Do I make myself clear?
像清澈的湖水一样 弗雷德
As an unmuddied lake, Fred.
像盛夏蔚蓝的天空一样清楚
As clear as an azure sky of deepest summer.
你可以依靠我 弗雷德
You can rely on me, Fred.
好
Good.
好孩子
Good boy.
我理解你喜欢音乐
I understand you're fond of music.
我为你安排了一个小小的惊喜
I have arranged a little surprise for you.
惊喜?
Surprise?
一个我希望你能喜欢
One that I hope that you will like
把它当作
as a
怎么说呢
how shall we put it
当作我们新的理解的象征
as a symbol of our new understanding.
在两个朋友间的理解
An understanding between two friends.
我被治愈了 全好了!
I was cured, all right!